ucalgary.ca 2016-11-30

# University Policy

                                                                           University Policy
                                                                                     University Procedure
                                                                                             Instructions/Forms
            Privacy Policy
             Classification                                                Table of Contents
                          Information Management
                                                                                 Purpose                1
             Approval Authority                                                  Scope                  2
                         General Counsel                                         Definitions            3
                                                                                 Policy Statement       4
             Implementation Authority
                                                                                 Responsibilities       5
                         Access and Privacy Coordinator
                                                                                 Appendices             6
             Effective Date                                                      Procedure              7
                         May 1, 2007                                             Instructions/Forms 8
                                                                                 Parent Policy          9
             Latest Revision
                                                                                 Related Information 10
                         March 15, 2011
                                                                                 References             11
                                                                                 History                12
Purpose     1      The University of Calgary is committed to protecting the privacy of individuals
                   who work and study at the University or who otherwise interact with the
                   University in accordance with the standards set out in the Freedom of
                   Information and Protection of Privacy Act.
                   The purpose of this policy is to tell individuals how the University fulfills that
                   commitment.
Scope       2      This policy applies to Personal Information in the custody or under the control of
                   the University of Calgary.
Definitions 3      In this policy:
                         a)   “Collection” means the act of gathering, acquiring, recording, or
                              obtaining Personal Information from any source and by any means.
                         b) “Consent” means a voluntary agreement to a Collection, use, and/or
                              Disclosure of Personal Information for defined purposes.
                         c) “Disclosure” means making Personal Information available to a Third
                              Party.
                         d) “FOIP” refers to the Freedom of Information and Protection of Privacy
                              Act.
            The electronic version is the official version of this policy.                                 Page 1 of 6

                            e) “Formal Access Request” refers to a request for access to information
                                 which cannot be answered through existing or established processes. A
                                 Formal Access Request is processed under terms and conditions set out
                                 in FOIP.
                            f)    “Personal Information” means information about an identifiable
                                 individual including but not limited to:
                                      i. name
                                     ii. home address
                                    iii. SIN
                                    iv. gender
                                     v. income
                                    vi. family status
                                   vii. student grades
                                 Personal Information does not include work product information, that is,
                                 information that is prepared or collected by an employee as part of the
                                 employee’s work responsibilities.
                            g) “Third Party” means a person, a group of persons, or an organization
                                 other than the individual the information is about. An employee of the
                                 University, acting in his or her official capacity, is not considered a third
                                 party.
                            h) “University Official” refers to an individual who has authority to act in an
                                 administrative capacity at the University.
Policy Statement 4     Accountability
                       4.1 Responsibility for ensuring compliance with the provisions of FOIP rests
                               with the University’s General Counsel.
                       4.2     The General Counsel may delegate responsibility for managing activities
                               relating to the Collection, accuracy, protection, use, Disclosure and
                               retention of Personal Information. This delegation will be detailed in the
                               Delegation of Authority which is attached as an appendix to this policy.
                       4.3     The General Counsel will appoint an Access and Privacy Coordinator to:
                               a) coordinate the development and implementation of policies and
                                     procedures to manage the University’s compliance with Part 2 of FOIP;
                                     and
                               b) provide support services to University officials on matters pertaining to
                                     the protection of Personal Information.
                       Collection of Personal Information
                       4.4 The University will collect Personal Information only for the following
                               purposes:
                               a) the information relates directly to and is necessary for an operating
                                     program or activity of the University;
                               b) the Collection of information is expressly authorized by an enactment
                                     of Alberta or Canada; or
                 The electronic version is the official version of this policy.                       Page 2 of 6

              c) the information is collected for the purposes of law enforcement.
      4.5     The University will collect Personal Information directly from the individual
              the information is about unless there is a reasonable requirement to
              collect from another source and the indirect Collection is permitted under
              FOIP.
      4.6     Details relating to the purpose for the Collection of Personal Information
              will be provided to the individual when Personal Information is collected
              directly from the individual.
      Use of Personal Information
      4.7 Personal Information will not be used for a purpose other than the
              purpose for which it was collected or for a use consistent with that
              purpose except with the Consent of the individual or as permitted under
              FOIP.
      Disclosure of Personal Information
      4.8 Personal Information will only be made public or disclosed to a Third Party
              under the following circumstances:
              a) the Disclosure is for the purpose identified at the time of collection or
                    for a purpose consistent with the original purpose,
              b) the individual the Personal Information is about has consented to the
                    Disclosure,
              c) the Disclosure is not considered to be an unreasonable invasion of
                    privacy, or
              d) the Disclosure is required, permitted or authorized under FOIP.
      4.9     It is not considered to be an unreasonable invasion of a student’s privacy
              to release the following information to a Third Party:
              a) dates of registration at the University of Calgary;
              b) faculty/department or program of registration at the University of
                    Calgary;
              c) degree(s)/diploma(s) awarded from the University of Calgary;
              d) convocation dates;
              e) attendance at or participation in a public event or activity related to
                    the institution (e.g. graduation, sporting or cultural event); or
              f) Personal Information already in the public domain.
              NOTE: this information may be restricted in specific cases for security
              reasons. Any restrictions on disclosure will be noted as a "Negative Service
              Indicator". These service indicators are displayed and can be accessed
              from the main components in the PeopleSoft Student system.
      4.10 It is not considered to be an unreasonable invasion of an employee’s
              privacy to release the following information to a Third Party:
              a) employment status;
              b) business address, telephone number, e-mail address;
              c) job title;
              d) job profile;
The electronic version is the official version of this policy.                        Page 3 of 6

              e)   rank, job family;
              f)   salary range;
              g)   discretionary benefits;
              h)   relevant educational qualifications;
              i)   attendance at or participation in a public event or activity related to
                   the institution (e.g. sporting or cultural event);
              j) Personal Information already in the public domain; or
              k) publications listed in an academic staff member’s annual report.
              This information is generally available in public or published sources such
              as the telephone directory, the calendar, or the collective agreement.
              Requests for the personal information of an employee that is not readily
              available will be referred to the employee’s supervisor or to Human
              Resources.
      4.11 Teaching material and research information of employees may be
              disclosed to University Officials for administrative purposes.
      Accuracy
      4.12 The University will take reasonable steps to ensure that Personal
              Information in its custody or under its control is as accurate and complete
              as is necessary for the purposes for which it is to be used.
      4.13 Individuals will normally be able to correct or update certain categories of
              Personal Information, such as contact information, on their own. To
              request a correction of other types of Personal Information, individuals
              may contact the data custodian.
      4.14 If the data custodian is unable to make the correction for any reason, the
              individual may file a request, in writing, for correction with the Access and
              Privacy Coordinator.
      4.15 If the University is satisfied that the individual’s request for correction is
              reasonable, the correction will be made as soon as possible.
      4.16 The University will also send the corrected Personal Information to any
              organization to which it was disclosed during the year before the
              correction was made if the information could have been used to make a
              decision about the individual.
      Retention
      4.17 The University will retain Personal Information only as long as necessary
              for the fulfillment of its purposes as defined in its retention rules.
      Security
      4.18 The University will take reasonable steps to protect information from
              unauthorized access, collection, use, disclosure or destruction.
      4.19 When the University retains an external organization to undertake work on
              its behalf that involves the disclosure of Personal Information, the
The electronic version is the official version of this policy.                       Page 4 of 6

              University will enter into an information sharing agreement with that
              organization. The information sharing agreement will set out conditions
              that ensure that the University’s responsibility for the protection of
              Personal Information will be fulfilled by the external organization on its
              behalf.
      Access
      4.20 Individuals have a right of access to Personal Information about
              themselves in the custody or under the control of the University subject to
              specific and limited exceptions as provided in FOIP.
      4.21 Employment or academic references will only be disclosed to the subject
              with the consent of the referee.
      4.22 A request by an individual for access to his/her own Personal Information
              should initially be directed to the data custodian or by following existing
              procedures for access to the information. If there is no process in place
              and/or the data custodian is unable to provide access for any reason, the
              applicant may file a Formal Access Request with the Access and Privacy
              Coordinator. A Formal Access Request must be made in writing.
      4.23 A request by one individual for access to the Personal Information of
              another individual should initially be directed to the data custodian. If the
              data custodian is unable to provide access for any reason, the applicant
              may file a Formal Access Request with the Access and Privacy Coordinator.
              A Formal Access Request must be made in writing and must be
              accompanied by a $25 application fee.
      4.24 A request by a University Official for access to the Personal Information of
              an employee or student should be directed to the data custodian. Access
              will be provided when the University Official needs the information in
              order to do his/her job or when the University Official is operating within
              his/her mandated authority.
      4.25 The Access and Privacy Coordinator will establish and maintain the
              procedure for responding to Formal Access Request.
      4.26 Fees for producing records in response to a Formal Access Request for
              your own personal information may be charged if the total fee is estimated
              to be greater than $10. Fees will be assessed in accordance with the Fees
              Schedule (Schedule 2) attached to the FOIP Regulation (Alberta Regulation
              200/95).
      4.27 Fees for producing records in response to a Formal Access Request for the
              Personal Information of another individual will be assessed in accordance
              with the Fees Schedule (Schedule 2) attached to the FOIP Regulation
              (Alberta Regulation 200/95).
      Questions, Complaints
The electronic version is the official version of this policy.                     Page 5 of 6

                         4.28 The Access and Privacy Coordinator will respond to questions or concerns
                                 about the University’s management or treatment of personal information.
                         Violations
                         4.29 Violators of this policy may be subject to penalties under University
                                 regulations, collective agreements, and under provincial and federal law.
Responsibilities   5     5.1 Approval Authority
                              a) ensure appropriate rigour and due diligence in the development or
                                   revision of this policy.
                         5.2 Implementation Authority
                              a) ensure that University staff are aware of and understand the
                                   implications of this policy and related procedures;
                              b) monitor compliance with the policy and related procedures;
                              c) regularly review the policy and related procedures to ensure consistency
                                   in practice;
                              d) sponsor the revision of this policy and related procedures when
                                   necessary;
                              e) appoint a Policy Advisor to administer and manage these activities.
Appendices         6     Delegation of Authority
Procedure          7     Formal Access Request Procedures
Instructions/Forms 8     Request to Access Information Form
                         Request to Correct Personal Information Form
                         Reference Consent Form
Parent Policy      9     Acceptable Use of Information Assets Policy
Related            10    Collection Notices
Information              Dealing with Confidential Records
                         Disclosing Personal Information of Employees to Third Parties
                         Disclosing Personal Information of Students to Third Parties
                         Disclosing Personal Information of Employees to the Subject
                         Disclosing Personal Information of Students to the Subject
                         Duty to Assist
                         Recruitment and Selection
References         11    Freedom of Information and Protection of Privacy Act (RSA 2000, Chapter F-25)
History            12    Approved: April 15, 2007
                         Effective: April 15, 2007
                         Revised: s. 4.9(b) revised to include the terms ‘department’ and ‘program’;
                         February 24, 2010.
                         Revised: s. 4.29 added, March 15, 2011.
                   The electronic version is the official version of this policy.                  Page 6 of 6
